<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Kyle's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://mskyle.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mskyle.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-29T18:54:07-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://mskyle.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kyle]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First post, last blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://mskyle.github.io/blog/2013/08/29/first-post-last-blog/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-29T16:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mskyle.github.io/blog/2013/08/29/first-post-last-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was raised in an outdoorsy family, and when I was 13 my family went on an all-day cross-country ski trip. Like, we gathered at my uncle&rsquo;s house on a nice Saturday morning in February and we started skiing around 10AM. We stopped for a nice lunch on a frozen lake, and then kept skiing for five more hours until it was raining. Then we trudged up a hill to wait by the side of the road in the gathering twilight while my dad and my uncle hitckhiked back to the cars, because even after seven hours of skiing (did you know that cross-country skiing is one of the most intense forms of aerobic exercise?) we hadn&rsquo;t gotten to the planned finish point of our little ski tour.</p>

<p>That evening, I swore that I would never go cross-country skiing again. My parents, who are smart people, realized that there was no point in pretending that the day had been anything other than an epically horrible slog through the woods of Maine in soaking wet clothes (and did I mention that I was pretty well the slowest of all my cousins, including Loren, who was six?) and so they agreed that I would not be expected to go cross-country skiing in the future. I think they thought I would cave and ski again after a few trips, or certainly by the next winter.</p>

<p>They were wrong. While the rest of the family would go skiing, I would stay in my uncle&rsquo;s house and read books or watch old movies. I did not go cross-country skiing again for eighteen years.</p>

<p>But eventually I did. Nowadays I&rsquo;m more of a snowshoer (snow-shoer?)than a XC skier, and I don&rsquo;t own my own skis or boots, but I can on occasion be lured out onto a snow-covered golf course.</p>

<p>Anyway, that&rsquo;s a long way of saying that I said I wasn&rsquo;t going to start any more blogs. I guess leaving a trail of discarded online presences is just a fact of modern life, but some part of me can&rsquo;t help but see it as evidence of failure or a lack of stick-to-itiveness: the circa-1996 personal homepage I made about how much I liked five dollar bills and doing laundry, the defunct livejournal, the not-updated-for-three-years knitting blog, the travel blog that I sometimes remember to update after a big trip, the tumblr and the Instagram and who even knows what else.</p>

<p>But here I am. Blogging again. Let&rsquo;s call it a project blog: I will keep this blog while I&rsquo;m at <a href="http://www.launchacademy.com/">Launch Academy</a>, and I&rsquo;ll talk about learning to code and my Breakable Toy project, and probably some other stuff. Then if, come November, I decide to let this blog join the others in the virtual blog graveyard, that will be OK, because that was always the plan. And if I want to keep going with it, that&rsquo;s cool too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
